Hello, everybody.
Welcome back to the IELTS Intermediate Speaking Course by PrEP.
In this lesson, we will focus on part one in the speaking test.
Part one of the IELTS speaking test lasts around four to five minutes.
In this part, you'll be asked questions about yourself.
The topics can be familiar or unfamiliar, but all the questions will be about you and your experiences.
In this video, we will look at seven main types of IELTS speaking part one questions.
The first question type is personal habits.
These questions ask about what you usually do in your daily life.
The topics often include your daily work and study routine, morning habits,
or more specific ones such as shopping or reading.
These questions usually start with what do you usually do or do you often?
To get a high score, you need to use adverbs of frequency like normally or regularly.
Don't just say what you do, explain the routine.
For example, what do you usually do in the morning?
I will give you 30 seconds to think about your answer.
30 seconds start now.
A good answer would be I tend to wake up quite early
around 6 a.m. and go for a quick run.
After that, I usually have a light breakfast before starting my studies for the day.
The second type is preferences or in other words, you will be
asked about likes and dislikes in a wide range of topics.
They can include but are not limited to food, types of transport, music, TV, art, clothing and so many others.
For this question type, you will hear phrases like do you prefer
A or B or which do you like more or what is your favorite?
To answer, you should answer directly about your preferences and then add
further details to extend it, which we will learn in the next videos.
To get a high score, you should learn different ways of expressing what you like or don't like.
For example, do you prefer traveling by train or bus?
You have 30 seconds starting now.
To answer, you could say, I'd rather travel by train, it's significantly
more comfortable than the bus and I find I can actually relax or read a book while I travel.
Type 3 is past experiences.
While the first two types mainly require you to use the present
tenses, this is a test of your grammar, specifically your past tenses.
You will often be asked about your past experiences in questions about
your childhood, your hometown or traveling.
These questions have phrases like did you, when you were a child or how has something changed?
To answer this question type, you must use past tense verbs correctly
and try to extend your answer with details, for example, an event in the past or a memory.
For example, did you enjoy sports when you were at school?
You have 30 seconds to think and answer.
My answer is yes, I vividly remember playing football every single afternoon with my classmates.
I was quite competitive back then and I loved the feeling of being part of a team.
The next question type is questions about frequency.
This is similar to questions about habits, but the focus is strictly
on how often you do an activity like visiting family, going to the cinema or using social media.
So the topics can vary for this type, from common topics like
friends and family, hometown TV, to slightly less common ones like computers
and technology, newspapers or gifts.
These questions almost always start with how often do you, and to
answer, you should use adverbs of frequency and varied time phrases.
You should avoid saying always every time, but instead you can use
phrases like on a regular basis or once in a while, for example, how often do you go to the cinema?
Your 30 seconds to think and answer starts now.
You might answer as, to be honest, I go once in a blue moon, I find it much more convenient and cheaper to just
watch movies at home on my laptop.
Next we have comparisons.
This question type requires you to compare two things, like living in the city versus the countryside.
These questions usually contain phrases like, is it better to, or what are the differences between?
To answer, you should use comparative adjectives and linking devices to show
the relationships between two things, for example, is it better to study alone or with friends?
And you have 30 seconds to answer, starting now.
An answer could be, it depends on the subject.
Studying alone is better for deep focus, whereas studying with friends is
great for brainstorming or discussing difficult concepts.
The next question type is questions about opinions.
The examiner will ask what you think about a certain topic.
You might think that this sounds more like a question type in
IELTS Part 3, but you can still find opinion questions in Part 1.
The big difference is that while Part 3 questions ask about more
abstract or broader issues, Part 1 questions ask about your opinion on daily matters.
Your answers in Part 1 are only shorter, preferably with only 2 -3 sentences.
This question usually starts with, what do you think about, or do you think it is good or important to?
To answer, you can open with phrases such as, in my opinion,
in my view, or as I see it, before sharing your opinion and further expansion details.
For example, do you think it is important to learn a second language, and 30 seconds for you to think and answer begins.
A good response is, in my opinion, it is vital.
It doesn't just help with communication.
It also opens your mind to different cultures and ways of thinking.
Finally, we have questions about future predictions or likelihood, where you
will be asked about a future plan or whether you think something will happen in the future.
Therefore, you will need to use future tenses and the answers.
You may find this question type in topics such as work and
study, travel, technology, and so on.
The questions may start with, do you think you will, or is
it likely that, since we don't know the future for sure, when
answering these questions you should use probability words like, I expect, possibly, or it's highly likely.
For example, do you think you will live in another country in
the future, and you have 30 seconds, starting now.
You could say, I think I will.
After graduation, I have decided to continue improving my English
through self -study so I can eventually move to the UK for my master's degree.
Now let's review what we learned so far through some interactive questions.
Great job, everyone.
Understanding these seven question types will help you answer each of them better.
In the following videos, we will go over techniques to brainstorm ideas and extend our answers in part one.
I'll see you soon.